<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A most learned, conscientious, and devout exercise, or, Sermon of self-denyal, (preached or) held forth the last Lord's-day of April, in the year of freedom the 1st. 1649, At Sir P.T.'s house in Lincolns-Inn-Fields / by Lieutenant-General O. Cromwell ; as it was faithfully taken in characters by Aaron Guerdo. And now published for the benefit of the New Polonian Association, and late famed ignoramus juries of this city.</title>
            <author>Guerdon, Aaron.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2907A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R175855</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">61297094</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 61297094</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180626</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09552)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180626)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2837:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A most learned, conscientious, and devout exercise, or, Sermon of self-denyal, (preached or) held forth the last Lord's-day of April, in the year of freedom the 1st. 1649, At Sir P.T.'s house in Lincolns-Inn-Fields / by Lieutenant-General O. Cromwell ; as it was faithfully taken in characters by Aaron Guerdo. And now published for the benefit of the New Polonian Association, and late famed ignoramus juries of this city.</title>
                  <author>Guerdon, Aaron.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year of freedom 43 [i.e. 1692?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Humbly dedicated to the worthy Protestant-hop-merchant, and the rest of the ignoramus-brethren."</note>
                  <note>Aaron Guerdon is a pseudonym. Cf. ESTC.</note>
                  <note>Sir P.T = Sir Peter Temple. Cf. ESTC.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658 --  Humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Government, Resistance to --  Humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180626:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A moſt Learned, Conſcientious and Devout EXERCISE, OR SERMON OF Self-Denyal, (Preached or) Held forth the laſt Lords-day of <hi>April,</hi> in the <hi>year of Freedom</hi> the 1ſt. 1649.</p>
            <p>At Sir <hi>P. T</hi>'s Houſe in <hi>Lincolns-Inn-Fields.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Lieutenant-General <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> Immediately before his going for <hi>Ireland;</hi> as it was then faithfully taken in Characters, <hi>By</hi> AARON GUERDO.</p>
            <p>And now publiſhed for the Benefit of the New POLONIAN ASSOCIATION, and late Famed IGNORAMUS-JURIES of this CITY.</p>
            <p>Humbly Dedicated to the Worthy <hi>Proteſtant-Hop-Merchant,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Ignoramus-</hi> Brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the <hi>Year of Freedom</hi> 43.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:180626:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180626:2"/>
            <head>A moſt Learned, Conſcientious, and DEVOUT EXERCISE OR SERMON of Self-Denyal, Held forth by Lieutenant-General <hi>Oliver Cromwell.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rom. 13. verſe 1.</bibl>
Let every Soul be ſubject unto the Higher Powers; for there is no Power but of God: The Powers that be, are ordained of God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>DEarly beloved Brethren and Siſters; it is true, this Text is a Malignant one; the wicked and ungodly have abus'd it very frequently; but (Thanks be to God) it was to their own Ruine; yet their abuſe of it ſhall not hinder us to make a right uſe of it. Every thing is ſubject to be abuſed, be it never ſo holy and good: the men of God, the Creatures of God, all are ſubject to Injuries, and Abuſe, The Councel of State, the Parliament, the Army, the General, have been (and daily are) abuſed: Nay, even my ſelf have not eſcaped the violence of thoſe Seducers, whoſe Tongues are ſharper than a Two-edg'd Sword; My very Face and Noſe are weekly malign'd and ſcandaliz'd by thoſe ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling <hi>Mercuries, Elencticus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Pragmaticus;</hi> inſomuch, that (were it poſſible) they would raiſe a Faction in my Forehead, and make Mutiny amongſt my very Teeth. 'Tis true, I have a very hot Liver, and that is the cauſe my Face and Noſe is red;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180626:3"/>
for my Courage and Valour lies in my Liver, not in my Heart, as other mens do: never any man could ſay my Heart was ſtout; indeed the General's lies there, and that's the reaſon his Face is pale. You all know I never was a Drunkard, although when I was at loweſt I had Beer enough, (for you know I had near relation to a Beer-Brewer) and I had always Money to buy me Wine, if I pleaſed: ſo that I might have been a Drunkard if I would; yet (you know) I am a temperate ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber man, elſe I had not been ſo good a Souldier. But what is it that the Malignants will not abuſe, who lett not to abuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? I'll warrant you they would abuſe our very Wives too, if they durſt; and I am affraid ſome of them do—You know what I mean; but no more of this at preſent.</p>
            <p>My Text (you ſee) is Scripture, and Scripture muſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved (next to our <hi>Divine Revelation)</hi> let it be what it will; But the Malignants would interpret it <hi>One way,</hi> and we (the Saints) <hi>Another;</hi> Now, let any body judge who are to be believed, They or We; whether (Iſay) thoſe Ungodly <hi>Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers,</hi> that fought to uphold <hi>Tyranny,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> or <hi>We,</hi> that in uprightneſs of our Hearts, fought for <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and <hi>for Establiſhing the Kingdom of King</hi> Jeſus. Surely, Beloved, it is <hi>We</hi> that are in the right of it; I think none of you will deny it.</p>
            <p>But now I ſpeak of Kings, the main Queſtion is, VVhether by the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> are meant <hi>Kings</hi> or <hi>Commoners?</hi> Truly (Beloved) it is a very great Queſtion amongſt thoſe (they ſay) that are Learned; But I think verily they make more ſtir about it than needs; For, may not every body that can read obſerve, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in the plural number, <hi>the Higher Powers:</hi> now, had he meant ſubjection to a King, he would have ſaid, <hi>Let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Soul be ſubject to the Higher</hi> Power; that is, if he meant <hi>One Man;</hi> But you ſee he meant more than one, for he bids us <hi>be ſubject to the Higher</hi> Powers; that is, the <hi>Councel of State,</hi> the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> and the <hi>Army.</hi> I hope I have cleared this point; ſo then I will come cloſer to the words themſelves,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180626:3"/>
and ſhew you truly and plainly (without any gaudy Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick) what they ſignifie unto us, that you be not deceived; And I tell you, this is not to be done by every Spirit, but only by ſuch that are more than ordinarily endowed with the Spirit of diſcerning; I confeſs, there are many good Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men amongſt you, that intend well, and ſpeak well, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand well; but yet cannot apprehend well all things that lurk in Scripture-language, for lack of a ſufficient meaſure of the Spirit; They muſt be inwardly called thereunto, or elſe they are ſubject to Error, and Miſconſtructions.</p>
            <p>Well then, you ſee who are fitteſt to interpret; I preſume you alſo believe God hath abundantly ſupplied me; I do not boaſt of it, but I ſpeak it to his Glory who hath vouchſafed to take up his Lodging in ſo vile, contemptible, unſwept, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waſh'd, ungarniſh'd a Room, as is this unworthy Cottage of mine; But it was his will, and I am thankful for it.</p>
            <p>Now, the words of themſelves are very natural; they are plain, not difficult, but proſtrate themſelves in a moſt perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner.</p>
            <p>For firſt, Beloved, by theſe words, <hi>Let every Soul,</hi> &amp;c. we may underſtand that every one of us have Souls; whence I raiſe this point of Doctrine, <note n="*" place="margin">1 Doctrine.</note> 
               <hi>That it is an Ungodly, Irreligious, Prophane, Idle Tenent, among the men of the world to think or ſay that Women have no Souls; Mark my Beloved, to think or ſay,</hi> &amp;c. For there are many now-a-days, that think, and will not ſpeak what they think; and others ſpeak, and will not think what they ſpeak: But we are none ſuch, dear Siſters, it is a great abuſe to your Honourable Sex. And now truly I will turn to you only; for you have been our daily and <hi>Nightly Comforters,</hi> indeed lau you have: You have raiſed our drooping Spirits, though never ſo much dejected; You have got us Stomachs, when we had none, and furniſhed us with Fleſh on all occaſions; We never found you unwilling or unready to ſerve us on all occaſions, when we were fartheſt from home.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:180626:4"/>
Believe it, when I lay before <hi>Pembroke</hi>-Caſtle, my Landlady where I quarter'd (who had once been a <hi>Malignant,</hi> and then but newly crept into the <hi>State of Grace;)</hi> ſhe (I ſay) had a <hi>Good Soul</hi> within her, ſhe was brim-full of the Spirit, and yet was very handſom, which is ſtrange; for ſeldom we find a Perfection without an Imperfection; Commonly, women that are <hi>Fair,</hi> are either <hi>Falſe,</hi> or <hi>ſoul within;</hi> but to me ſhe was neither; and yet I do not ſpeak this to condemn Beauty; for it is of ſingular Comfort, and good Uſe; and thoſe that be <hi>Fair,</hi> may be <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Good,</hi> as in this ſingle inſtance; But this is <hi>ſecundum Majus &amp; Minus,</hi> (as the <hi>Logicians</hi> cant it) <hi>ſome are better than other ſome;</hi> that's the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of the <hi>Latine;</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I have found great and vaſt difference in women.</p>
            <p>Then again, when I came into <hi>Yorkshire</hi> I met with Mrs. <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> the Eſpouſed of that Valiant and Honourable Saint Major-General <hi>Lambert;</hi> ſhe is, I ſay, a woman not very Fair, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, but of as large a Soul, and as full of the Spirit, as any I ever yet met with; I profeſs, I never knew a woman more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with thoſe Heavenly Bleſſings of Love, Meekneſs, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſs, Patience and Long-ſuffering; nay, even with all things that may ſpeak her deſerving the name of a Saint, every way; yet (I ſay) as to her Perſon, ſhe was not very Beauteous, and Comely; for ſhe is ſomething Foggy, and Sun-burnt; which is ſtrange, in that cold Northern Climate; But what Nature hath denied her of Ornament without, I found ſhe had within her a Soul, a devout ſweet Soul; and, God knows, I lov'd her for it.</p>
            <p>Thus we find then, both by Scripture and experience, that all of us have Souls, Men and Women; But then again, Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſome have good Souls, and ſome have bad: Mrs. <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> hath a good Soul, and no doubt (nay I know) many of you that be here are and have good Souls within you; The <hi>Cavaliers</hi> and their Queans are the bad Souls; they ſerve, and are ſubject to bad and ungodly men; Men did I call them, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Devils, that would devour us, and drink themſelves drunk
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180626:4"/>
with the Bloud of the Saints. By this then it is evident, who have been, and who are the good Souls.</p>
            <p>From whence then I raiſe this my ſecond Doctrine, <note n="*" place="margin">2 Doctrine.</note> (rather point of Faith) <hi>That we are not to believe nor to account any to be, or to have good Souls, but thoſe that are of the Family of the Saints.</hi> I had almoſt ſaid, <hi>Of the Family of Love,</hi> but that it is a particular Sect, ſomething differing from ours.</p>
            <p>Come on then; <hi>Let every Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What ſhall every Soul do?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Be ſubject to the Higher Powers,</hi> &amp;c. whereby we ſee <hi>all Souls,</hi> good and bad, are bound to <hi>be ſubject. All-Souls-</hi>Colledg in <hi>Oxford</hi> muſt be ſubject to our Viſitors: <hi>All-ſouls-day,</hi> though a Superſtitious Holiday, kept by the Papiſts and Biſhops, (thoſe Peſts of the Church, which we have lately and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly extirpated) muſt alſo be Subject to thoſe uſes, our Powers ſhall allot or appoint it to; Your Souls, Brethen and Siſters, muſt be ſubject to perſwaſion, to love familiarly, and in entire Friendſhip, to all things that may increaſe and elevate the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; to kindle and take fire, like tinder upon every ſpark, and glance of our affection; Oh! My Dear Brethren, and Siſters, Love is the fulfilling of the Law, what need we more then? Love alſo, covers a multitude of Sins; Then it hides all our infirmities, had we according to this rule, loved one another; theſe differences and Bloud ſhed had never happened.</p>
            <p>Objection, <hi>But ſome will object and ſay, that there is a Luſt as well as Love; and ſo commixed, as not to be diſtinguiſhed; and many times on the conſequence of the other, to the Scandal and reproach of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> But I tell you, (Beloved) theſe nice and critical diſtinctions, are things had once like to have undone us; Luſt is nothing but the deſire of any thing; The Saints cannot err; (my Beloved) we deſire to enjoy one another, God forbid but that we ſhould help and comfort each other, and lay out, and extend our ſelves, as far and freely as may be, to aſſiſt each other in the free Embraces of the Spirit, the Law of Reaſon and Nature requires it of us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:180626:5"/>
Queſtion, <hi>But let us look a little further; to whom muſt eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Soul be Subject to?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Why <hi>to the Higher Powers.</hi> I have told you alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy what theſe Higher Powers are; they are the <hi>Council of State,</hi> the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> and the <hi>Army;</hi> and God forbid but that all men ſhould obey them; that is, all the people, every Soul of them, be ſubject to the <hi>Council of State;</hi> the <hi>Council of State,</hi> to the <hi>Houſe of Commons;</hi> they to the <hi>Army;</hi> the <hi>Army,</hi> to the <hi>General;</hi> and the <hi>General,</hi> to <hi>ME;</hi> To <hi>Me,</hi> (I ſay) who have Ploted, Adviſed, Councelled, and Fought (all accompanied with a continual ſeries of Succeſs) for both You and them for theſe ſeven years, and now at laſt have purchaſed your Freedom and Liberty. Dear Brethren, and Siſters, I ſpeak it not in oſtentation, but with thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and praiſe to him, who hath made me ſo uſeful an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in this work of Reformation; for, Beloved, it was I that juggled the late <hi>King</hi> into the <hi>Iſle of Wight.</hi> It was I that diſſolved the Treatiſe; It was that ſeized upon, and hurried him to <hi>Hurſt-Caſtle;</hi> It was I that ſet <hi>Petitioning</hi> on foot throughout the Kingdom, againſt the perſonal Treatie, and for bringing the <hi>King,</hi> and other <hi>Capital Offenders</hi> to <hi>Justice;</hi> It was I that contrived (with my Son <hi>Ireton)</hi> the long <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance</hi> of the <hi>Army;</hi> It was I that preſcribed the erecting of the <hi>High Court of Justice,</hi> which brought the <hi>King</hi> to His Tryal; In a word, it was I that (in effect) cut off His Head, and with it all the <hi>Shackles</hi> and <hi>Fetters</hi> of the <hi>Norman</hi> Slavery, and Bondage; It was I that cut off the Heads of <hi>Capel, Hamilton</hi> and <hi>Holland;</hi> It was I that ſurprized the <hi>Levellers</hi> of <hi>Burford,</hi> and <hi>Northamtonſhire;</hi> It was I that broke their deſign, and cut off <hi>Thompſon</hi> for example, and ſo diſperſed and appeaſed the reſt; By which I have healed all the late Diſtempers in the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> whereby the whole Land is reſtored to this bleſſed Peace, Tranquility and Plenty we now enjoy; And therefore (I ſay) I may juſtly (without ambition) Stile my ſelf the Auhor of all the Kingdoms preſent and future Happineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:180626:5"/>
It is true (Beloved) the General is a Stout and Valiant man, and hath great appearance of God in him; but fitter to be <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive</hi> than <hi>active</hi> in Affairs of State; He is fitter for a Charge, than for Council; and (under the Roſe) he wants Brains to do any thing of moment; but indeed, this I may ſay for him, he is a man that doth not ſeek himſelf; I never found him wilful, but willing to ſubmit to better Judgments than his own. For, when <hi>Sedgwick,</hi> (that faſt and looſe Prieſt of <hi>(ovent-garden)</hi> upon the King's Tryal, had writ to his Lady, to adviſe him to remit the Execution of that Sentence, and wholly (at leaſt) to waſh his hands of his death: He (honeſt man) preſently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted me with the buſineſs, and ſhew'd me the arguments given to perſuade him againſt it, and freely referred it to my Judgment; and the <hi>28th.</hi> of <hi>January</hi> (being the <hi>Lords-day)</hi> at night, I went to him, at his Houſe in <hi>Queen-ſtreet,</hi> (attended with two Troops of my own Regiment of Horſe) to remove the ſcruples he had made upon receiving that raſcally Prieſts Letter, or to ſecure him by force, if I had any ways found him to continue averſe, and would not be ſatisfied; But he (good man) gave me thanks for my pains, and told me I had fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved him. All this (Beloved) I ſpeak in honour of the man; But truly he is <hi>too Great</hi> to be <hi>ſo good as we must have a General;</hi> and you know he is a Lord, and unleſs he be a Lord and no Genleman, (as I believe he will not acknowledge himſelf) he is not for our turn. Beſides, he is (you ſee) ſo eaſily ſeduced, and led away by every wind of Doctrine, by mean appearances, and ſhadows of reaſon. Truly, Beloved, I think my ſelf and my Son <hi>Ireton</hi> may prove of greater uſe to the <hi>Republick</hi> than any other; and if we be but once by the acknowledgment of the people choſen Governours thereof, we queſtion not but to anſwer their expectations to a Hairs breadth; which, if ever it come to paſs, (for the Kingdom <hi>[Obſerve]</hi> cannot be ever ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled upon any firm or laſting Baſis or Foundation without it;) then I and my Son <hi>Ireton</hi> are <hi>the Higher Powers</hi> here meant in my Text, to whom ſubjection is commanded; for (as I told
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180626:6"/>
you before it cannot be to one ſingle man, it muſt be to Two, or more; And truly if the People ſhall think of us, as we think of our ſelves, worthy of that Truſt; we ſhall diſcharge it faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and ſtudy to merit it at their hands; But, miſtake me not, I do not mean by merit, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do; That is to ſay, to deſerve it at their hands, for the good works we have, or ſhall do; No no, we will acknowledge it all out of the free Grace and Mercy of the People: For when we have done all we can for them, we muſt acknowledge our ſelves moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Servants.</p>
            <p>I thank them, they have already made me General for <hi>Ireland;</hi> and you know I am now juſt upon the point of going there, in great hopes of reducing thoſe Rebellious Traytors to your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; But Beloved, ſo many of you as go along with me, muſt be mindful of my Text; That is, you muſt be in all things Subject to <hi>Me,</hi> and my Leiutenant-General; when we bid you go, you muſt run; when we bid you Storm, you muſt do it, though it be againſt nothing but Stone Walls; You owe to us your Lives and Fortunes, your Limbs and all that you have: And that without Grumbling, for you muſt in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects ſubmit to the <hi>Higher Powers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In verity, this expedition againſt <hi>Ireland,</hi> is like to prove a very difficult thing, unleſs I can in policy, engage <hi>Owen Roe.</hi> If not, to joyn with <hi>Jones, Monk</hi> and <hi>Coot;</hi> yet to keep off at a diſtance with <hi>Ormond.</hi> I am Beloved, about it, and I ſhall do my utmoſt endeavors to ſet him and <hi>Inchiquin</hi> at variance; And yet at that very inſtant, will I loſe no time nor opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to re-oblige him to the <hi>Parliament;</hi> For you all know what <hi>Inchiquin</hi> is, I have him—but I will not ſay how—an Act of Indempnity it is probable tied in a ſtring of a five thouſand Pound bag, may work a Miracle; for he, good man, is but miſguided, he ſtands not upon ſuch punctilio's of Honour as <hi>Ormond</hi> doth. In truth Beloved, this <hi>Ormond</hi> is a very ſhrewd man, and were he not one of the <hi>Wicked,</hi> a man highly deſerving (not ſo much for his knowledge and experience
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180626:6"/>
in Military Affairs; which yet may challenge ſome due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Honour) for the diligence and faithfulneſs in the truſt committed to, and repoſed in him; <hi>Valour</hi> I will not allow him, I can only term it deſperateneſs, and that he wants not. But remember how politickly he carried himſelf in the buſineſs of <hi>Dublin,</hi> after we had totally ſubdued the common enemy here firſt; how dextrouſly in the firſt place did he avoid the meſſages and Commands of the late King, for delivering up <hi>Dublin</hi> into our hands, (the which order we extorted from him) how ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully did he baffle the Commiſſioners we ſent to treat with him about the Surrender; at what diſtance ſtill he kept them, urging the Captivity of the King, to excuſe his obedience; and how often, and upon what ſleeveleſs errands he ſent them back, to re-inforce their inſtructions; whileſt all that while, he was underhand endeavouring to know the Kings pleaſure, by the hand of his own Meſſenger; And when he was ſatisfied of the realty, he trucked with us for his own Security and ſatisfaction; nay more, when he had ſtood on the receipt of ſome thouſands, before he would be induced to ſurrender; you ſhall hear how he then ſerves us: For notwithſtanding that I cauſed the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> by their Letters voluntarily to aſſure him the full double the Sum he demanded, upon condition he would quit the King, and declare for our Intereſts, and that hereunto, he had returned a fine Silver Tongu'd reſponſe in anſwer to the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> and to indempnifie him and his Followers, for all things ſaid or done in relation to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Wars, and four Thouſand pound to recompence for his great Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Loſſes, with this additional aſſurance that he ſhould (ſoon after ſurrender) be re-inveſted with full Power in the ſaid Government again, by Commiſſion from the <hi>Parliament;</hi> Yet, no ſooner was <hi>Dublin</hi> delivered to us, by virtue of the King's Letters and his Paſ-port ſent him, but he in contempt of all our fair and civil offers, Tranſports himſelf to <hi>France,</hi> abruptly waving both our Proffers and Protection.</p>
            <p>This, Beloved I inſtance not to juſtifie him, in his Rebellions
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180626:7"/>
courſes againſt the Nation, for I will uſe my utmoſt endeavours to deſtroy him for it: But to let you ſee how gloriouſly, though in the things that are wicked, and unjuſt, he appears in the eyes of the World; in being ſo true and firm to his Truſt, on whoſe fidelity is not to be corrupted by Gold, nor good Preſerments; and continues faithful to the very laſt, when in one ſenſe it was altogether uſeleſs, nor will I let to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him to be no leſs formidable then faithful and ſedulous.</p>
            <p>For certainly he hath gone very near to practice all Intereſts, and pick'd out of them a numerous Army, over whom he hath placed good Officers; <hi>Good,</hi> (ſaid I) I don't mean thereby <hi>Godly Officers,</hi> for they are all of them <hi>Prelatical</hi> and <hi>Popiſhly affected;</hi> but I mean <hi>Try'd Souldiers,</hi> ſuch as will not eaſily turn their backs on an Enemy: Theſe I muſt endeavour to oblige; and I muſt confeſs, they have alſo a good Strength by Sea, and a number of wilful, reſolute, ſtout Fellows for Mariners, who are in great heart, by reaſon of the <hi>many</hi> and <hi>great</hi> Prizes they have taken from us: But what of all this? Shall we therefore be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged? God forbid. The more numerous the Enemy is, the greater ſhall the Victory over them be; The more difficult the work is, the more Glory to <hi>God,</hi> and Honour to <hi>Us;</hi> The ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler their Pockets are, the worſe they will fight, you know by experience. The Plunder of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> gave us the Victory at <hi>Naisby;</hi> there you ſaw the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> choſe rather <hi>to leave their King to His ſhifts,</hi> than <hi>ſhift from behind their Cloak bags.</hi> Believe it, Gentlemen, we ſhall <hi>(by Faith)</hi> meet with many advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges againſt them. <hi>R.</hi> himſelf (and I know who elſe, will do us ſome good, though it be but croſſing of Proverbs; and if I hear but once that <hi>Culpepper</hi> or <hi>Hide</hi> is there, doubt not but all is our own. I cannot recount a Tithe of them; but this I am ſure, the honeſt Citizens have feaſted us to good purpoſe; for upon that occaſion we had their promiſe to advance Money afreſh for <hi>Ireland; (Sam Nombre On Menſare,</hi> that is <hi>French,</hi> Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> whereof is) without Weight or Meaſure; verliy they are of a ſtiff necked Generation; An exceeding
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180626:7"/>
Meek, and Humble People, from being Mutinous and Factious, and indeed Beloved; It was no ſmall work, we had to ſubdue the malignant Spirits of the City; Conſidering how audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly once they withſtood our Authority; and deſpiſed our Government, how peremptorily they petitioned for a perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Treaty; with the King, and ſent their Servants into <hi>Colche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Surry,</hi> and <hi>Kent,</hi> to inforce thereunto, how bitterly they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed and railed againſt the proceedings of the Parliament and Army; how largely they contributed to bring in a Foreign Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion, towards us whilſt yet, they denyed us the Payment of our arrears, or to continue the neceſſary Taxes or Exciſe, for our future maintanance, who had preſerved them and their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly's from the rapine and cruelty of a Barbarous Enemy, but Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Brethren, I mean not to rip up old matters; Let it ſuffice that, being warned by that miſhap, you alſo fall not into the like Sin of Diſobedience to Higher Powers; there being no Powers but of God, the Powers that be, being ordained of God.</p>
            <p>Objection, <hi>But it may be, ſome here may object and ſay you have clearly open'd and prov'd that You and Your Son</hi> Ireton <hi>are the Higher Powers here appointed by God; then how ſhall we be ſecure in your abſence, from the Malitious Plots and Contrivances of the</hi> Papiſts <hi>and</hi> Malignants <hi>on the one hand, and thoſe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ground</hi> Moles, <hi>the</hi> Presbyterians <hi>and</hi> Levellers <hi>on the other; who, all conſpire, though for different, ends the ruine of the Power, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially hot-headed</hi> Lilburn, <hi>and the reſt with him, in durance whoſe unquiet turbulent Spirits can never be quelled, but by a</hi> Common-wealth; <hi>They being ſo implacable and deſperate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Truly Beloved, you do very well to make theſe doubts, I like theſe doubting Chriſtians, provided they be not Jealous Chriſtians, but in anſwer hereunto, I lay this down for a ſure maxim, that God himſelf always protects thoſe Powers he ordains; and he never ſuffers them to be flung off the Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; but for our Sins or Miſgovernment in the ſame, and I think as hitherto you are all witneſſes that I have done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing yet, whereby to incur the diſpleaſure of the Almighty.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:180626:8"/>
But more particularly, ſee how far my Policy hath taken care for you, and the Peace of the Nation in my abſence; for ſuppoſe that <hi>Lilburn</hi> and the reſt of our <hi>Factious Enemies</hi> (as God knows we have too many) ſhould ſtrive to alienate the hearts of the People from us, And to uſurp the Rule and Dominion to themſelves; If that convenient ſtrength were not left, and one ſo well fitted with Policy and Courage to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them; I have therefore taken care that my Son <hi>Ireton</hi> ſhall ſtay amongſt you, and my Noble Colonel <hi>Lambert</hi> ſhall go my <hi>Leiutenant General</hi> in his ſtead; And my Son you know, wants no Spirit, if he did, he ſhould never have Married my Daughter; as to his Policy you have as little reaſon to doubt, as I of his Fidelity; the large Remonſtrance renders him, I think, very clear handed and Subtle: And with him I will leave a ſufficient Strength, both of Foot and Horſe; Which together with the City Forces, of which we are now ſure (the <hi>General</hi> alſo, ſo Popular and Valiant a man, ſtaying here alſo to overſee them,) ſhall, you need not fear, ſuppreſs all Inſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Tumults whatſoever; however, I have left ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections with my Son <hi>Ireton,</hi> about <hi>Lilburn</hi> and the reſt, as if ever hereafter they obſerve him or them, to ſtir up the People to Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or to ſcribble any thing as formerly againſt our procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; that he ſhall forthwith execute Military Juſtice upon them, <hi>Ad terrorem mortua ne mordent,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> is, <hi>dead men tell no tales,</hi> ſince neither our mercy, nor the ſence they have of the uprightneſs of our <hi>Cauſe,</hi> will invite them to forbear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpattering the <hi>Innocent Robes of this Infant Eſtate.</hi> And now Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, as we muſt not conceal any thing from one another (ye all being my Souldiers, and with your Wives my intimate privadoes and boſom Friends) I ſhall make bold to acquaint your ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in inſtancing another doubt, with a danger at the end of it, which although it may ſtartle you at the firſt ſight, yet be of good courage, be faithful, and ſtrong, it admits of any eaſie So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, <hi>viz.</hi> About the Accord now on Foot, between the <hi>Scots</hi> and their new King. Truly I muſt confeſs, my deſigns were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180626:8"/>
till now ſo diverted and confounded; for I muſt tell you, I always reverenc'd that ſhort but pithy Precept of <hi>Machiavel, divide and reign;</hi> So long as I could keep them at odds amongſt themſelves, I feared not but to order them as I pleaſed. But now it is too true, that both the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> of that Kingdom, have attainted <hi>Argile</hi> of Treaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> For hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the hands of the <hi>Scots,</hi> until we Executed that exemplary piece of Juſtice upon the King; And that they therefore intend to cut his Head off, which if they do, they deſtroy our only Friend in that Kingdom: And the differences on Foot there, muſt needs expire with his death; which being once done, there will nothing be left to be done, but to vie Authority with us, and threaten us a ſecond Invaſion; for you muſt underſtand the <hi>Scots</hi> are a Warlike People, that there is nothing will make them ſooner Rebel, then Plenty and Idleneſs; They cannot be long at Peace; If they were quiet amongſt themſelves, they muſt Invade us. Now Beloved, to preſerve our ſelves againſt them, if it ſhould come to the pinch, we had better quit thoſe out-houſes of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and though that were burnt, it matters not, ſo we be ſecure at home; To which end I have reſolved, that if they cut off the Head of <hi>Argile,</hi> or otherways diſable him to proſecute our Intereſt there; that then I will wave the War in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and keeping the fore-door of this Nation cloſe ſhut, bend all my Forces to defend the back-door againſt that perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious People; And this I perceive to be the ſureſt way, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded I can make choice of truſty and able Men to ſecure the <hi>Ports</hi> and <hi>Towns,</hi> and <hi>In-land Garriſons,</hi> without revolts, or Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery; and this will be the eaſier done, conſidering the Men and Money we have at our diſpoſals; I tell you, one Thouſand ſhall ſlay there <hi>ten Thouſand,</hi> and in a ſhort time make them a little contemptible miſerable People; and at laſt root them out from off the face of the Earth, and poſſeſs our ſelves of their Lands, for an Inheritance to us, and our Generations for ever.</p>
            <p>But I have ſtrayed too far from my Text, I will now come to the remaining words of it, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:180626:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>For there is no Power, but of God.</hi> viz. <hi>the Councel of State, the Houſe of Commons, the Councel of War,</hi> and all the High-Court of Juſtice are of God; and the following words of my Text, give you the reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Powers that be, are ordained of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be they juſt or unjuſt, they are all of God; and ſo requires your <hi>Paſſive,</hi> if not <hi>Active obedience;</hi> For God ordained them, as he did that Tyranical Power of the late King, and thoſe Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Gods the Biſhops; ſo he ordained us for their ſins, to pluck them down, and as he hath graciouſly removed thoſe wicked Powers; ſo he hath appointed us to preſerve, cheriſh, comfort, and relieve the <hi>Saints,</hi> our Lot is fallen in a pleaſant place, and <hi>We,</hi> now enjoy all their Lands and Eſtates; that <hi>We</hi> might Rule and Govern the Land, in <hi>Sincerity</hi> and <hi>Truth;</hi> by diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting Juſtice equally, and impartially, to every Soul accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will; but the time is paſt, and my buſineſs has a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral now, requires my Preſence and Councel; I deſire there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Dear Brethren, and Siſters; that you daily power out your Prayers and ſupplications for us, and for our ſucceſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wicked and ungodly that are riſen up againſt us; and that you ceaſe not to comfort one another, with <hi>Mutual Embraces</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Kiſſes,</hi> to delight and ſweeten your paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages through this vale of miſery, And that you take ſpecial care to ſtrengthen and corroberate your ſelves, with all mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate uſe; of the Creatures, that I may find <hi>Oyle in your Lamps when I return.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Let us call upon God in Prayer.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
